let's look at the solution to our
virtual index physically tag cache
aliasing avoidance quiz we want no
aliasing which means the index bits have
to come from the page offset the page
has 2 to the 13th bytes so the page
offset has 13 bits in the address
breakdown for accessing the cache that
means that our index and offset for the
cache need to fit in 13 bits the 16 byte
block size means that the cache block
offset is four bits that's how many bits
we need to tell us where in the 16 bytes
we are and that means that we have nine
bits for the index we can use fewer but
that would make the cache even smaller
we cannot use more because then we would
get aliasing so the maximum cach size
will be when it has 2 to the 9th sets so
we have 2 to the 9 sets time 2 to the
4th bytes in each block times it's a
four-way set associative cache so we
have 2 to the 2 four blocks in a set so
this is basically bytes per block blocks
per set how many sets and that amounts
to 2 to the 15th bytes in the cache so
the answer here is 32 kilobytes which is
2 to the 15th bytes so we cannot have a
cache that is larger than 32 kiloby and
yet it avoids aling with these
parameters know that really these two
have to be equal to the page size
because two to this number of bits time
2 to this number of bits has to be equal
to two to this number of bits so really
the maximum size of the cache here is
the page size times the associativity
and the only way to avoid aliasing in a
cache while making it larger is to
increase associativity